你没被跟踪?
You weren't followed?
没有
No.
还是进来吧
Better come in.
吉姆 别信任任何人
Trust no one, Jim.
尤其是大人物
Especially not in the mainstream.
坐吧
Sit down.
我知道你还有一个匈牙利的身份可用
I understand you still have one H ungarian identity running?
是的
I do.
我想派你去布达佩斯
I want you to go to Budapest.
这是秘密任务
'This is not above board.
没有其他人知道
'Nobody else knows.
他们要取我的命 吉姆老弟
'They're after my head, Jim boy.
你明白吗?
'Do you understand?
我得到一个情报
'I have had an offer of service.
一个匈牙利的将军
'A Hungarian general wants to come over.
我想让你跟他碰面
'I would lik e you to meet him.'
他有我想要的信息 吉姆
He has some information that I need, J im.
什么信息?
What information?
宝藏
Treasure.
他知道苏联人安插在英国情报机关的内线的名字
'He has the name of the mole
'the Russians have planted in the British intelligence service
他们都是圆场高层 （圆场：英国情报机构的代称，位于剑桥圆场）
'right at the top of the Circus.
这些烂苹果 吉姆
'There's a rotten apple, Jim.
我们要把他找出来
'We have to find it.'
来点炖杂肉吧？尝过这个没？
是的，我尝过
这东西很好，比炖牛肉要强 但是你现在在布达佩斯吃不到了
为什么？
因为那些猪都去莫斯科了
我何时能见到你的朋友？
你会见到的，不吃点吗？
容我失陪一下
住手!
Stop!
谁让你开枪的？
谁他妈的让你开枪的？
你会为我做见证吗?
Would you witness this for me?
我希望能做得更多 老总
I wish I could done more, Control.
你已经尽力了 潘西
You did all you could, Percy.
哎 一个人应该知道什么时候退场
Well, a man should know when to leave the party.
史迈利呢?
What about Smiley?
史迈利和我一起走
Smiley is leaving with me.
你这个滑头 伊斯特哈斯
You little prick, Esterhase.
《锅匠 裁缝 士兵 间谍》
各位 我们可以开始了吗?
Gentlemen, shall we start?
副部长拉康已经在等您了 潘西先生
U nder Secretary Lacon is ready for you, Sir Percy.
财政部不懂
The Treasury don't understand.
为什么情报局不能直接申请
Why can't the intelligence service simply put in a request
普通的增拨资金
for a general increase in funding
那不就可以支持你们的特殊任务了吗?
and then you account for the spend on your special operation?
“巫术行动”需要保密
Operation Witchcraft needs to remain secret.
-它有自己的一套 -这正是我们担心的
- It's a fiefdom of its own. - Yes, that's what's worrying us.
这整一件事让人摸不着头脑 不是吗?
The whole thing's very unaccountable, isn't it?
这个房子在伦敦哪儿大家都不知道
And this London house that nobody knows the address of,
真的有这个需要吗?
is that really necessary?
绝对有必要 要保护我们在苏联的线人
Now more than ever. We need to protect our Soviet source.
你要我们在哪里跟他碰面? 咖啡店吗?
So where do you propose we meet? In a caf?
这房子的租金和花费差不多是平常的两倍
The rent and rates on this house have doubled.
在核武上就花了好几百万
We spent millions on nuclear warheads.
我们不过要几千块租个房子
We're asking for a few thousand for a house.
我好奇卡拉在克里姆林宫里 （卡拉：苏联情报机构头目）
I wonder if Karla has the same problem
是不是有着同样的烦恼
with the Treasury at the Kremlin.
听好 没有人低估
Look, nobody underestimates
你们工作的重要性
the importance of the job you chaps are doing.
但去年在布达佩斯发生的事
But what happened in Budapest last year,
那简直是一个灾难
that was a disaster.
坦白说
With respect, sir,
被杀的人不是你们办公室里的公务员
it wasn't one of your civil servants that got killed, was it?
现在说的也不是战壕里的士兵
Now this isn't about soldiers in trenches any more.
-是我们在前线的... -罗埃!
- We're the front line now... - Roy!
25年以来 我们唯一一次可以走近卡拉
For 25 years we've been the only thing standing between them and Karla
走近莫斯科 甚至走近了他妈的第三次世界大战
and Moscow and the third bloody world war.
听好了 大臣非常满意你们目前的成果
Look, the Minister's very pleased with your progress so far.
不过 他对你们
He's less pleased, though,
跟美国人缺少协作这点不甚满意
with the lack of progress with our American cousins.
你看
You see,
在他们的眼里
in their eyes,
你们还是烂船一艘
you're still a leaky ship.
怎样?
Yes?
电话有人找你 长官 像是急事
'Someone on the line for you, sir. Seems urgent. '
好的 把电话接进来
All right, well put him through.
-喂? -是副部长拉康吗?
- Hello? - 'Ls this U nder Secretary Lacon? '
是的
Yes.
我叫里基・塔尔
My name's Ricki Tarr.
-你想怎样? -我要见你
- 'What do you want? ' - I need to meet you.
如果你想确认我的身份 可以去找我在圆场里的上司
If you need to confirm who I am, you can talk to my boss at the Circus,
彼得・吉勒姆
Peter Guillam.
只能是吉勒姆 不能找别人
But only Guillam, no one else.
都处理掉了吗?
You got clearance for that?
我不负责在外面捉人
Well, I'm not bloody chaining it up outside.
我提醒你 这里也许已经不安全了 到处是刺客
Mind you, no better off in here with this bunch of bloody cut-throats.
连他们的牙齿里也藏着武器
They'd have the gold out of your teeth.
我比布兰德早一步瞅到一个新来的女孩 他见过她没?
Thought I'd pop in and catch a glimpse of the new girl before Bland gets to her.
啊 对 金发美女 贝琳达
Ah, yes. Belinda the blonde.
-他见过她没? -他当然见过了
- Has he seen her yet? - Of course he has.
今早一来到的这儿的头等大事
Came down first thing this morning.
贝琳达
Belinda.
-彼得・吉勒姆 -喂 彼得 我是奥利弗
- Peter Guillam. - 'Hello, Peter, this is Oliver.
我打电话来问一下...
'Just ringing to find out...
'So Winston Churchill saved your life, Edie.'
'I was working in the kitchen, getting dinner ready.
'And he was late, you see.'
- 'During a raid? ' - 'During a raid, you see.'
'He said, "Why aren't you in that shelter?"'
- 'Why weren't you? ' - 'Well, because... '
老总的事 我很遗憾 史迈利先生
I was sorry to hear about Control, Mr Smiley.
他说塔尔从电话亭打电话给他
'He said Tarr called him from a phone box.'
他说有只地鼠
He said there's a mole,
潜伏在圆场的高层
right at the top of the Circus,
已经好几年了
that he's been there for years.
这就意味着
It does mean
你现在相当适合帮我们调查这件事
you're rather well placed to look into this matter for us now,
不是吗?
doesn't it?
作为一个局外人
Outside the family.
我已经退休了 奥利弗
I'm retired, Oliver.
你炒了我
You fired me.
事实上
The thing is,
之前老总还在的时候
some time ago before Control died,
他跟我提过类似的想法
he came to me with a similar suggestion.
圆场有地鼠
That there is a mole.
他没有跟你提起过他的猜疑吗?
He never mentioned his suspicions to you?
没有
No.
我只是以为.... 你是他的人
Oh, I just thought that as you were his man, so to speak...
你怎么回应他的?
What did you say to him?
我当时以为他犯了偏执病
I'm afraid I thought his paranoia had rather gotten the better of him
打算自己拆自己的台
and he was going to pull his whole house down.
还有布达佩斯那个烂摊子
That bloody mess in Budapest.
去他的 乔治
Damn it, George.
这是你的时代 你的辉煌
It's your generation, your legacy.
我应该想到的 如果这属实的话 你会想...
I would have thought, if there's any truth in it, you'd want to...
彼得留下给我用吧
I'll k eep Peter.
还有那个退休警察 孟德尔
And there's a retired Special Branch man, Mendel.
我也要
I should lik e to have him.
- Lift up.
And quickly down again.
我知道有个地方 在利物浦街附近的一家小旅馆
There's a place I know, sir. A little hotel near Liverpool Street.
请小心点　这是乔治王朝风格的
Be careful with it. Please. It's Georgian.
我朋友需要一个安静的工作环境 蒲波-格雷汉姆太太
My friend wants peace and quiet in order to work, Mrs Pope Graham.
没有干扰的环境
No disturbances.
她的真名只有格雷汉姆
Her real name is just Graham.
加上“蒲波”是为了表示等级
Added the Pope for a touch of class.
彼得 你能拿到老总公寓的钥匙吗?
'Peter, did you get the k eys to Control's flat? '
# And did those feet in ancient time
# Walk upon England's mountains green #
噢!
Oh!
乔治!
'George! '
乔治! 给我进来!
George, get in here!
乔治
George.
坐下
Sit down.
看看这份不知所谓的东西
Tak e a look at this nonsense.
这是苏联最高指挥部
Report by Soviet high command
就近期他们在黑海的海军演习发回的报告
on their recent naval exercises in the Black Sea.
这正是海军部向我们
Just what the admiralty has been begging us
乞求的情报
for some information on.
-你从哪里搞到的? -不是我搞来的
- Where did you get this? - I didn't.
不是我 是潘西和他的小团伙拿来的
Percy and his little cabal walk ed in with it.
-老总 这... -闭嘴
- Look, Control... - Shut up.
文风差得令人发指
Style appalling.
明显是彻头彻尾地瞎编乱作
Patently a fabrication from beginning to end.
-不过倒像是真的 -如果内容属实就等于挖到了金矿
- Just could be the real thing. - Well, if it's genuine, it's gold dust.
但这个话题总是惹人猜疑
But its topicality mak es it suspect.
史迈利生性多疑 潘西
Smiley is suspicious, Percy.
从哪儿弄来的? 通过什么渠道得来?
Where did it come from? What's the access?
我的一个新线人
A new secret source of mine.
可是他怎么可能弄到…?
But how could he possibly have access?
他连最高决策层的机密都有办法搞到
He has access to the most sensitive levels of policy-making.
我们把这个情报源称之为“巫术”
We've named the operation Witchcraft.
史迈利 潘西和他的搭档们已经绕过了我们
Oh, Percy and his pals bypassed us, Smiley.
直接去找部长了
Gone straight to the minister.
潘西可以对他新伙计的身份
Percy has been allowed to k eep the identity of his new friend
绝对保密
top secret.
部长与我一致认为这里充斥了太多不清不楚的事情
The minister agrees too many secrets are blown around here.
接二连三的失败 数不清的丑闻
Too much failure, too many scandals.
-可靠的情报却少得可怜 -潘西说到点子上了 老总
- Too little solid intelligence. - Percy does have a point, Control.
我们该对抗的是共产主义 而不是自己人
We should be fighting Communism, not each other.
这些争斗毁了我们的名声 也让我们失去了同盟伙伴...
Meanwhile we're losing our reputation, our partners.
你们这些恶毒的美国佬!
Your bloody Yank s!
我们已经受够了! 是时候改变了
We've had enough! There's going to be changes.
我们要想清楚 是要活在过去 还是要创造未来
We need to decide if want to be part of the past or part of the future.
从哪儿来的给我滚回哪儿去
I should have left you where I found you.
-听好! -老总...
- Look! - Control...
滚! 全都给我滚!
Out, all of you!
如果“巫术情报”是真的...
If Witchcraft is genuine...
再也没有东西是真的
Nothing is genuine any more.
乔治...
George...
你要我把东西搬到旅馆去吗?
Do you want me to get this stuff over to the hotel?
谢谢 随便放
Thank you. Er, anywhere will do.
-彼得? -嗯?
- Peter? - Hm?
彼得 我需要你帮我做点事...
I need you to do something for me.
你到圆场去
I'd lik e you to go to the Circus.
在当值室里的文件柜里
'Ln the cabinet at the duty officers' station
放着近期退休人员的记录
'are records of staff recently retired.
你拍成照片拿给我
'I'd like photographs of them
还有潘西・阿勒莱恩着手重组的圆场架构图表
'and of the diagram of the Circus's reorganisation under Percy Alleline,
别漏了秘密行动基金的支出表
'along with a list of all payments made from the Reptile fund.'
-有什么可以帮你的吗? 比尔 -我在找老大
- Help you with anything, Bill? - I was just looking for his Majesty.
他在顶楼踱步呢
Well, he's out walking the battlements.
喔
Oh.
-听说你出了点意外 彼得 -对啊 被抽屉拉手弄伤了
- Heard you had an accident, Peter. - Yeah, I cut my hand open on a drawer.
你们什么时候能在这里添些新家具啊?
When are you going to get some new furniture up here?
我会跟伊斯特哈斯反映的
I'll have a word with Esterhase. We'll mak e it a priority on the top floor.
我们楼上的人会优先考虑这件事
-你要去哪儿? -吃午饭
- Where are you off to? - Lunch.
一起好吗?
Want some company?
根据人事文件
According to the personnel files,
有七个人是够年龄退休
seven were due for retirement anyway.
其他四个人也看不出可疑的地方
Another four don't seem particularly mysterious.
杰里・威斯特贝在12月4日被解职
Jerry Westerby was dismissed December 4.
康妮・沙赫斯11月28日退休
Connie Sachs retired November 28.
也就是你和老总被迫出局两周以后
That's just two week s after you and Control were forced out.
-回牛津 谢谢 -在一点十五分
- Return to Oxford, please. - That's 1. 15.
潘西一向反对
Percy has always resisted any proposal
扩大“巫术情报”的使用范围的提议
of a wider exploitation of Witchcraft's intelligence.
别给我扯官腔 拉康
Drop the bloody jargon, Lacon.
时至今日 我还是拒绝跟我们的盟国分享“巫术”情报 大臣
I've refused to share Witchcraft with our allies so far, Minister.
贪婪的家伙
Greedy boy.
毫无疑问地我的目标在一步一步地实现
My goal has been to establish its track record beyond all doubt.
我看现在是时候去找我们的美国战友了
I think the time has come to approach our American brothers-in-arms.
他们会再次拉我们入伙吗?
- Will they tak e us back into bed? - I'm not interested in a one-off trade.
只做一次的买卖我没兴趣
我要的是能长期接触到美国的情报
I want on-going access to American intelligence.
你认我们能办到么?
You think we can get it?
只要掌握了“巫术”情报
With Witchcraft on our side, we can get anything we bloody well want.
我们想要得到什么都不成问题
好
Fine.
去做吧
Carry on.
谢谢
Thank you.
And I strik e thee down...
噢 我...
Oh, I, er...
不能喝酒的 医生的命令
Not supposed to. Doctor's orders.
讨厌的乔治
Wicked, wick ed George.
我不知道你怎么样 乔治
I don't know about you, George,
反正我觉得亲临其境
but I feel seriously under-fuck ed.
我听说安恩又离开你了
I heard Ann left you again.
她不配拥有你 乔治
She doesn't deserve you, George, not one hair on your head.
连你的一根头发都不配 根本都不配
我退休后不久你就离开了圆场
You left the Circus shortly after I retired.
不是我要离开 我是被炒的
I didn't leave. I was dismissed.
像垃圾一样被扔了 跟你一样
Chuck ed out on the rubbish heap, lik e you.
什么理由?
Why?
波里雅科夫
'Polyak ov.
你记得他吗?
'Do you remember him? '
苏联大使馆的人
'From the Soviet Embassy? '
阿里克塞・波里雅科夫
'Alexsey Polyak ov, cultural attach?here in London.
在伦敦的文化参事 - 波里雅科夫
十五年前他来到的时候
'When he arrived here 15 years ago, I requested he be check ed out.
是我提出要查他的
对波里雅科夫的评级比洗衣粉还白 没必要查
'He was graded whiter than white. Didn't put a foot wrong.'
但是你不认同?
'But you disagreed? '
你肯定听过一个传言
'There's a story you must have heard
卡拉组织了一个秘密组织
'that Karla has set up a secret cell.
成员都是前军人
'The personnel are all ex-military,
专门受训从事深入渗透的特工 地鼠
'trained to handle deep-penetration agents, moles.'
传言从来就没消停过 康妮
'There are always stories, Connie. '
但如果那些传言是真的呢?
'But what if this story was true?
在研究中心的某个晚上 我看到了些东西 乔治
'One night in research I saw something, George.
我们的好朋友波里雅科夫在柏林的“五一阅兵”礼上
'There was our friend Polyak ov at a May day parade in Berlin
接受敬礼
'receiving a salute.'
为什么要向一个文化参事敬礼?
'Why would you salute a cultural attach? '
莫非波里曾是战场上的前辈?
'Exactly. Unless he was a war veteran himself.'
如果是真的 他为什么要隐瞒呢?
And if he was, why hide the fact?
那你怎么做了?
What did you do?
我直接走到伊斯特哈斯和阿勒莱恩面前
I went straight to Esterhase and Alleline.
这里
Here.
如果我没弄错的话 波里雅科夫是卡拉训练的爪牙
Polyak ov is a Karla-trained hood if ever I saw one.
如果他在这里出现 那他肯定是安插了地鼠
If he's here, it must be because he's running a mole.
你不要再管波里雅科夫的事
You're to leave Polyak ov alone.
你对他有点着迷了
You're becoming obsessed with him.
-你现在做事掌握不了分寸 -太荒谬了!
- You're losing your sense of proportion. - But that's ridiculous.
也许你是时候离开 回到现实世界中去了
Perhaps it's time you went out into the real world.
但又有什么关系呢? 圆场的老人已经散的差不多了
What does it matter? Old Circus is gone anyway.
看看这个
Here we are.
年少无知的我们
The N ursery in our day.
吉姆・普莱多
Jim Prideaux.
和比尔・海顿 两个人必定站到一块儿
And Bill Haydon. Together, of course.
形影不离
The Inseparables.
这是老总
There's Control himself.
大家都在
All my boys.
就像一个大家庭
All my lovely boys.
真是一段美好时光啊 乔治
That was a good time, George.
那可是战争啊 康妮
一场真正的战争
A real war.
会让英国人感到自豪
Englishmen could be proud then.
那么 我是对的?
So I was right, then?
波里雅科夫的事
About Polyak ov.
有地鼠?
There is a mole.
如果没处理好 就别来告诉我了
If it's bad, don't come back. I want to remember you all as you were.
我想把记忆定格在以前那个样子
潘西 这是你干的好事吗?
Percy? Percy, did you mix this?
哎呀 是我干的
Aye, I did so.
你这个吝啬的苏格兰佬
You Calvinistic, penny-pinching Scot.
你就不能向外订餐吗?
Can you nae learn to tak e a bloody order?
自己胡乱摆弄什么菜谱啊!
Nobody tampers with the recipe!
-我的确是按菜谱做的 -来
- I followed the recipe. - Come on.
跟猴子尿一样 得喝上五个小时才会喝醉
It'll tak e us five hours to get drunk on this monk ey's piss.
# He's not the first
好吧
- # He's not the first - Oh, well.
圣诞快乐!
- # He's the second best secret agent - Merry Christmas.
# I n the whole wide world
# He's not number one
# But not the worst
# He's just the second best secret agent
# I n the whole wide world
# He's every bit
# As good as what's-his-name
# With a dame
# Any dame
# And all those bullet holes are in his vest
# To prove you work a little harder
# When you're second best... #
-P夫人向你问好 -嗯?
- Courtesy of Mrs P. - H m?
你一夜没睡?
You been up all night?
是的
Yes.
那是什么?
What's this?
申请书 请求从秘密行动经费里提取一千磅现金
Request for ?1,000 in cash from the Reptile fund.
给一个叫埃利斯的人
To a Mr Ellis.
吉姆・普莱多的其中一个化名
It was one of J im Prideaux's work names.
普莱多一年前在匈牙利被杀了
Prideaux was killed in H ungary a year ago.
10月21日
October 21.
怎么会有人在他死后两个月给他一千磅呢?
So why was someone giving him ?1,000 two months later?
我在想他现在在哪儿呢?
I wonder where he is then, sir.
别闹了
Settle down now.
-发下去 -先生
- Hand those out. - Sir.
什么玩意啊? 我们的驼子老师?
What is it? The H unchback of Notre-Dame?
叮叮当 叮叮当!
The bells, the bells!
噢!
- Ohh!
过来这里
Come here.
-你叫什么来着? -罗奇 我叫比尔・罗奇 先生
-我是新来的 -新来的 嗯?
- I'm a new boy. - New arrival, eh?
-你什么来历? -我父母...
- What's the story? - My mother and father.
我爸离开了 所以...
My father left, so...
嗯
Hm.
账单 （Bill还有账单的意思）
Bill.
欠费账单
The unpaid Bill.
-有人这么叫过你么? -没有 先生
- Anyone ever call you that? - No, sir.
我认识不少人叫比尔
Known a lot of Bills in my time.
都是不错的家伙
They've all been good 'uns.
你有些什么本事呢?
What are you good at?
没什么 先生
Nothing, sir.
你是个不错的观察者 是吗?
You're a good watcher, though, eh?
孤独的人都善于观察
Us loners always are.
我敢说 比尔・罗奇是班里最好的观察员
Best watcher in the unit, Bill Roach is, I'II bet.
只要他戴上眼镜就没什么能逃过他的眼睛 对么?
- Long as he's got his specs on. Right? - Yes, sir.
是的 先生
这个好 非常好
This is good, very good.
在吗 里基
Hello, Ricki.
你丢了一个楔子
You've missed the wedge.
你去了哪了? 里基
Where have you been, Ricki?
他们要杀我
They're going to kill me.
-谁要杀你? -你们
- Who is? - Your lot.
你们 或者他们 被谁先找到就死在谁手上
Or their lot. Whoever gets me first.
我是无辜的
I'm innocent.
说得过去吧
Within reason.
我会尽力 你在这多久了?
How long have you been here?
抱歉 我已经没有地方可以躲了
Sorry, I've run out of places now.
我要见你
I needed to see you.
为什么?
Why?
有一个女人
There's a woman.
我要你把她换回来 从卡拉手上把她换回来
I need you to trade for her. I need you to get her back off Karla.
什么女人?
A woman?
她叫伊琳娜
Her name's Irina.
在去年的12月
'This was last November.
吉勒姆先生派我去伊斯坦布尔查一个俄国贸易代表
'Mr Guillam sent me to Istanbul to check out a Russian trade delegate
一个可能会转投我们的人
'who might be persuaded to defect.'
-塔夫蒂・西辛格 驻外代表 -嗯
'Tufty Thesinger, resident.' - 'Yeah.'
-喂 里基 -最近好吗? 兄弟
- H iya, Ricki. - All right, mate?
你认识他? 不 从来见过
'Did you know him? ' 'No, never met him.'
酒鬼一个
'Bit of a drink er.'
整天醉醺醺的
Hangover from hell.
一个蠢货
'Bit of a fucking idiot.
这个叫鲍里斯的俄国佬
'Apparently this Russian, name of Boris,
在夜总会夜夜笙歌
'was spending high and wide in the nightclubs. '
你的任务就是游说他倒戈?
'So you were sent to persuade this Boris? '
没错 他是典型的俄国佬
'Yeah. He was your typical Russian.
贸易代表团就知道没日没夜地饮酒作乐
'Trade delegation by day, out boozing every night.
好像都不用睡觉似得
'Didn't seem to sleep.
他们几乎都能认出塔夫蒂了 所以他不方便跟踪
'Tufty was worn out from following him around.'
我看今晚有的忙了 孩子
I think it's going to be a long night, son.
在塔克西姆 他最爱去的地方就是俱乐部
'His favourite haunt was this club in Tak sim.
那儿的地下室是藏污纳垢的地方
'Lt had a hellhole in the basement where the sailors and the tourists went.
供水手和旅客消遣的地方
反正我看了他一眼 就知道自己白来了
'Anyway, I took one look at him and I knew I'd wasted a journey.
鲍里斯不是什么代表
'Boris was no delegate.
比起代表团 他们更符合酒鬼这个身份
'What delegate bothers to play drunk er than he really is?
你得面对现实 不是吗? 史迈利先生
'You get to recognise your own, don't you, Mr Smiley?
鲍里斯就是个流氓
莫斯科中心出来的人 （莫斯科中心：指苏联情报机构）
'Moscow Centre trained.'
# Someone is waiting
# I mean just for you
# Spinning wheel
# Keep on spinning through, Drop all your troubles... #
我猜他在等着接头
'I guessed he was waiting for a connect.
或许在干投信的活儿
'Working a letterbox, maybe.
或许放线钓鱼 等着像我这样的人上钩
'Or trailing his coat and looking for a pass from some mug like me.'
所以第二晚我就去了进出口部
'So the second night I went to the import/ export outfit
塔夫蒂在密室架了一台加密电报机
'that Tufty had set up with a cipher room hidden in the back.
我给吉勒姆先生发了电报 “没有交易”
'I cabled "No sale" to Mr Guillam.
就是这样了
'And that was that.'
你第二天就要搭飞机回去
You were due to fly home the next day.
是
Yes.
但你没回去
But you didn't.
鲍里斯有个妻子
'Boris had a wife.
合法的妻子
'Common-law.
明显她也是代表团的成员之一
'Apparently she was a member of the delegation in her own right.
你曾经叫我相信自己对女人的直觉 史迈利先生
'You once told me to trust my instincts about women, Mr Smiley.
没错 我的直觉告诉我这个女人藏着宝藏
'Well, my instincts told me this woman had some treasure.
有一晚鲍里斯不在酒店 我就探入了她住的旅馆
'When Boris went out for the night, I found myself going into her hotel.'
所以你丢下了鲍里斯
'So you dropped Boris.'
我知道 那不合规矩
'I know. It was breaking protocol.
但可以说是我不由自主地行动起来
'But I was acting on my own initiative, as it were. '
你的男人就是个混账东西 不是吗?
Your man's a bit of a bastard, isn't he?
我只是想确认一下你没事 明白吗?
I just wanted to mak e sure you were all right, OK?
所以你就没有回来了?
'So you didn't come home? '
我本打算回来的
I would have.
鲍里斯那边是没门了 但是...
Boris was a dead end, but...
呃...
Um...
我能
I could...
我能感觉到她心里有事
I could sense something in her.
一个秘密
A secret.
你打算用什么方法把她的秘密套出来?
And how did you intend to get this secret out of her?
我用商人迈克・特仑奇的身份
'I played this businessman, Michael Trench.
跟她发生了一段假期恋情
'Holiday romance.'
可惜时间紧迫无法好好享受…
'I thought I'd tak e my time with it.'
我知道你是谁
I know who you are.
我有话要跟你们的上司谈
I want to talk to your boss.
老总
Control.
我有东西跟你们做交易
I have something to trade.
很重要的东西
Something big.
我想在西方开始新的生活
I want a new life in the West.
这就是我的开价
That's the deal.
你去告诉他们
You tell them.
你不能指望他们一下子就接受所有的开价
Look, you can't expect them to jump at every offer of service.
既然你不愿多说 那我也无能为力
If you won't tell me more, there is nothing I can do.
如果我向你坦白所有
If I tell you everything,
就等于把自己的性命交到你手上
I'm putting my life in your hands.
还有其他人的生死
And the lives of other people.
她告诉我她想要的是什么
'So she told me what she had to trade.
她的秘密
'Her secret.
我指的是
'I mean,
是所有秘密的源头
'the mother of all secrets.
我告诉她我意识到是关于圆场的
'I told her I'd alert the Circus.
她要我保证不会向伦敦透漏任何细节
'She made me promise I wouldn't give any of the details to London.'
-然后你同意了? -是的
'And you agreed? ' 'Yes.
我告诉你...
'I mean it was...
我都不敢相信自己掌握了这么重要的情报
'I couldn't believe I'd got hold of something this big.
我回到进出口部
'I went back to the import/ export,
给圆场发了个消息 标注为“最高紧急级别”
'sent the message to the Circus, graded, "Flash, highest priority",
只是说 我找到了一个想叛变的莫斯科间谍
'just that I had a Moscow-trained hood wanting to defect.'
你怎么还没走 伦敦站的人找上我了
You're supposed to have gone. London stations have been on to me.
他们要知道你到底在玩什么花样
Want to know what the hell you're doing.
滚你的
Fuck off.
还有吗? 里基
'Anything else, Ricki? '
我知道 对于圆场来说 我不过是剥头皮组的一个喽罗 （剥头皮组：圆场内负责搞暗杀、绑架、讹诈的机构）
I know what I am to the Circus. I'm one of the scalp-hunters,
做的是低贱卑鄙的差事
someone that you can hand your dirty little jobs to.
只是...
I just...
这件事我想由自己来解决
I just wanted to bring this one in myself.
我知道你的感受
Well, I understand how you felt.
你不想这么傻等着
You wanted to do something.
我汇报说 她声称掌握了
事关圆场生死的情报
Vital to the safeguarding of the Circus.
还有别的吗?
Anything more?
我还说了 她掌握的情报是关于双面间谍的
I said that she had information concerning a double agent.
我不过是想...得到足够重视 我想...
Look, I just wanted to get the proper attention. And I'd...
我让他们转告吉勒姆先生 这是我没有回去的原因
I told them this was the reason why I had not come home.
而不是因为我叛变了
It wasn't that I'd defected or anything.
-接下来你做了什么? -等着他们回复
- What did you do then? - I waited for a reply.
我就等了几个小时 我听到在黎明前的祷告
'I hung around for hours. I heard the lmsak call to prayer.
那是几点呢? 大约在凌晨的三点三十分
'So what's that? That's about 3. 30 in the morning.'
然后消息就发过来了
'Then the message comes through.
“知道了”
"'We read you."
那就是他们发过来的 什么也没用
'That was all they sent. Nothing.
根本说不通 像是他们在拖延时间
'Lt didn't mak e sense. It was lik e they were stalling.'
然后的事呢?
'Then what happened?
接下来 突然间...
'Then, all of a sudden...
...俄国佬开始行动了
'... the Russians begin to move.'
干的很漂亮 比我干的漂亮多了
'Lt was nice work. I couldn't have done it better myself.'
信号非常明显 我要警告她
'The message was quite clear. I needed to warn her. '
快接 快接 快接
Come on, come on, come on.
我四处寻找 我在飞机场找不到她
'I couldn't find her at the airport.
我甚至查了一遍航班表...
'I even look ed through all the flight lists and...
我跑去了码头
'I headed down to the harbour.
他们把她带上了去敖德萨的船
'They put her on a ship to Odessa.
我就知道这些了
'That's all I know.'
我已经...
I've...
我已经尽了全部的努力 史迈利先生 但是...
I've done a lot of things in my life, Mr Smiley, but...
我就是... 情不自禁地一直想着她
I just... I can't stop thinking about her.
她根本就不是我喜欢的类型
She wasn't even my type.
我想把她救出来 是我欠了她
I've got to get her out. I owe her that.
卡拉不会放过你
Karla will be looking for you.
有谁会放过我呢?
Everybody's looking for me.
你不可以留在这里
You can't stay here.
不安全
It isn't safe.
我说过 你可以上我的床 贝琳达 但是白天必须喊我长官
'I said, "You may fuck me but you'll call me "Sir" in the morning."'
知道了 就是来告诉你一声
'OK. Just need to let you know.
上个星期有人用我们的掩护身份飞到了巴黎
'Someone flew into Paris last week on one of our escaped passports.'
-还有呢? -是里基・塔尔
'And? ' 'lt was Ricki Tarr.'
为什么要告诉我?
'Why are you telling me? '
-不过是巧合... -你这个臭侏儒
- 'Lt could be coincidence... ' - 'You are a poisoned dwarf.
为什么不死去找大臣呢?
'Why don't you fuck off to his Majesty
别想把我拉进你们的小丑团
'and stop trying to involve me in your cabaret? '
伊斯特哈斯先生 也许是巧合 但是...
'Mr Esterhase: "It could be coincidence but..."
海顿先生打断了对话
'Mr Haydon interrupting.
你真是个臭侏儒 托比
"'You really are a poisoned dwarf, Toby.
为什么不死去找大臣呢?
"'Why don't you fuck off to his Majesty
别想把我拉进你们的小丑团
"'and stop trying to involve me in your cabaret?"'
你样子很疲惫
You look tired.
睡得不好
I didn't sleep well.
我想要你帮我拿点东西 彼得
You're going to do something for me, Peter.
我需要值班室去年11月的登记簿
I need the duty officer's log book for last November.
我不得不让你跑一趟楼上的虎穴
I'm going to have to send you up a floor into the lions' den.
如果你被抓到了
If you're caught,
不能把我供出来
很抱歉 不过你得孤身奋战
I'm sorry, but you're alone.
-去年11月的? -嗯
- Last November? - Hm.
吉勒姆先生!
Mr Guillam!
谢谢 布莱恩特
Thank you, Bryant.
家里还好么?
How's the family?
很好 今天需要上去办点事
Fine. Need to go up to the registry today.
明白 先生
OK, sir.
现在你要给包贴上黄色标签 先生
Now you'll need a yellow one for the bag, sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
-早上好 吉勒姆先生 -早 阿尔文
- Good morning, Mr Guillam. - Morning, Alwyn.
-需要我帮你看着包么? -谢谢
- Want me to look after that for you? - Thank you.
得给你贴个标签 吉勒姆先生
I'll need your chit, Mr Guillam.
否则道尔芬会骂死我 新规定
Dolphin will kill me if I don't. New rules.
贴吧
So, chit me.
谢
Thank s.
-真是惊喜啊 -彼得
- Sal, lovely surprise. - Peter.
-这周末有安排么? -还不那样
- What are you up to this week end? - Oh, you know.
去看我阿姨
Visiting aunts.
猜就是
I'll bet.
通道D
Corridor D.
二十八号在右手边的中间
The two eights are halfway on your right.
三十一号在下一个小间里
The three ones are next alcove down.
多谢
Thank s.
'Here's a request from Libby Barr from Bromley
'for "Mr Wu's A Window Cleaner Now". Tak e it away, George.'
你好 档案馆 我是阿尔文
Hello. Archive, Alwyn speaking.
麻烦你 我找一下吉勒姆先生
'Can I speak to Mr Guillam, please? '
我是修车师傅
I'm his car mechanic.
好的 我看看他有没有空接电话 请稍等
Well, I'll just see if he's available. Hold on, please.
# Mr Wu, what shall I do?
-噢 天啊! -电话找您 先生
- Oh, Christ! - Telephone, sir.
-谁啊? -外线电话 先生 说话声沙哑
- Who is it? - Outside line, sir. Someone rough.
先生?
Sir?
-喂? -你的齿轮箱废掉了
- Hello? - (Mendel) 'Your gearbox is bust, sir.'
去他妈 你就不能去修一修吗?
Damn it, can't you fix the bloody thing?
没法修了
'Can't be done, sir.
恐怕你要换一个新的齿轮箱
好歹先找一下经销商 你有他们的号码吗?
Well, phone the main dealership first. Have you got their number?
没有
'No.'
别挂线 阿尔文!
Hang on. Alwyn!
-阿尔文 -在
- Alwyn. - Sir?
包递给我 可以吗?
Get me my bag, will you?
-但是... -就一下子
- But... - J ust for a second.
谢了
Thank you.
别挂线
Hang on.
-喂? -我听着
- Hello? - 'I'm listening.'
-嗯 9-4-6 0-3-3-5 -记好了 先生
- Yes. 9-4-60-3-3-5. - 'Be right on it, sir.'
谢谢
Thank you.
彼得・吉勒姆
Peter Guillam.
你还真是难找啊
Could we see you, please?
潘西有急事跟你说
Percy would lik e quite an urgent word with you.
你现在去一下六楼 帮帮忙
If you can come now to the fifth floor that would be so kind.
行 没问题
Yes, of course.
你替我把那玩意儿扔到电梯里去
Throw that into the lift for me.
把它送上三楼 省得我一直写那些烦人的单子
Send it to the second floor, save me filling out bloody chits.
遵命 先生
Will do, sir.
你最近这些日子都在忙些什么呢...
So what have you been getting up to down there these days?
都在忙着泡妞吧
Apart from chasing our virgins.
有几个阿拉伯人看起来挺靠谱的
A couple of Arab ploys that look quite promising.
除此之外 乒乓球也打的不错
Apart from that, I'm getting quite good at ping-pong.
阿拉伯人
Arabs.
你可以租一个但是不能买下来 对吧 比尔?
You can rent one but you can't buy one. Right, Bill?
里基・塔尔最近怎么样了?
How's Ricki Tarr these days?
还行 我们每天下午都在福特纳喝茶
Fine. We have tea at Fortnum's every afternoon.
我要知道你跟塔尔的谈话内容
I require the matter of your discussion with Tarr.
我会跟他说的 他会很高兴的
I'll tell him. He'll be thrilled.
耸什么肩啊你?
What's that shrug for?
我跟你说的是你那个卖国贼
I'm talking to you about the traitor
那个在伊斯坦布尔杀了我们的人的卖国贼
who cut the throat of our man in Istanbul.
我说的是你那个烂部门的叛徒!
I'm talking to you about a defector from your own damn section.
我现在追究的是 你背着我勾结敌方的特工!
I'm accusing you of consorting with an enemy agent behind my back.
别他妈对我耸肩
Don't damn well shrug at me!
你想坐牢吗?
How would you lik e a term in prison?
我现在已经不跟他见面了
Well, I haven't been seeing him.
你好好弄清楚事实 少跟我嗦!
So get your facts straight and get off my back!
那我告诉你 塔尔最近刚到巴黎
So... if I told you Tarr had recently arrived in Paris,
你意外不?
would you be surprised?
塔尔做什么都不会让我意外
No, nothing would surprise me about Ricki Tarr.
如果我告诉你 我们查到
And if I told you we happen to know ?0,000 mysteriously appeared
上个月有一笔3万英镑的资金
神奇地出现在他的银行账户呢
in his bank account last month,
让你惊喜不?
would that surprise you?
你的人是叛徒 吉勒姆
Your man's a defector, Guillam.
几个月前被敌方收买了 现在他们把人送回来
Turned by the opposition months ago and now they've sent him back to us.
-什么目的? -别管什么目的
- What for? - Never mind what for.
要我们鸡犬不宁 那就是目的
To muddy the water, that's what for.
放一组烟雾弹耍得我们团团转!
To spread a whole lot of damn nonsense to get us chasing our tails.
现在关键是
The point is this.
他要回来了
He's heading for home.
你要是一看到他 立马给大人们报告
The first peep from him, you come to the grown-ups.
明白吗?
Understood?
现在在座的哪一位都可以 但不能对别的人透露!
Anyone you see around this table but not another damn soul.
出去
Get out.
彼得?
Peter?
谢谢你 贝琳达
Thank you, Belinda.
# Oh, Mr Wu
# What shall I do?
# Mr Wu... #
一切顺利吗?
All go smoothly, did it?
我要去旅馆见史迈利
I need to go to the hotel to see George.
史迈利先生不在酒店 改地点了
Mr Smiley isn't at the hotel, sir. Change of venue.
乔治?
George?
吉勒姆先生...
Mr Guillam...
抱歉 我拖了那么久才回来
Sorry it took me so long to come home.
里基一直在帮我们 彼得
Ricki has been helping us, Peter.
他告诉了我们他所有的冒险经历
He's been telling us all about his adventures.
他是个双面间谍! 乔治!
He's a double, George.
根本没有地鼠!
There is no mole. Whole thing's been thought up by Moscow.
整件事就是莫斯科那边编出来的谎言
卡拉花三万英镑收买了他!
Karla bought him for ?0,000.
我偷这个 就因为你
I stole that because of you.
就因为他 弄得我自己监视自己
I spied on my own because of him. Do you know how that mak es me feel?
你知道我是什么感觉吗?
里基...
Ricki...
你说你给圆场发了一封提及伊琳娜身份的电报?
you said you sent the Circus a telegram concerning Irina's information.
-没错 -哪一天?
- That's right. - What was the date?
他不会知道 因为根本就没有电报
He doesn't know because there was no telegram.
-整件事都是编出来的 -11月20日
- The whole thing is a fabrication. - 20th November.
肯定是11月20号 傍晚的时候
It must have been 20th November. Evening.
'lrina k ept telling me in Moscow Centre
'everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
11月20号这一页没了
- 'She told me Karla... ' - November 20th is missing.
有人藏起了自己的记录 难道你觉得
Someone is covering their track s, unless of course you think
这只是巧合?
that's just a coincidence?
那钱是怎么回事?
What about the money?
能换得他的地鼠的安全 3万英镑对卡拉来说不算什么
30,000 isn't so much for Karla to pay if it protects his mole.
恐怕圆场里有人知道了塔尔先生的事
I'm afraid someone in the Circus knows all about Mr Tarr
然后 用尽方法想诬陷他
and is doing everything they can to discredit him.
'... everything the Circus think s is gold is shit, made in Moscow.'
为什么不告诉我 你已经找到塔尔?
Why didn't you tell me that you had Tarr?
万一我在圆场失手了
In case I never made it out of the Circus.
我要休息一会儿
到时候你应该也看完了吧
I suppose you've got your reading to do.
上来
Come up.
我见过他一次
I met him once.
卡拉
Karla.
在55年的时候
In '55.
莫斯科中心四分五裂
Moscow Centre was in pieces.
大量的清洗行动
Purge after purge.
他们一半的特工外逃
Half their agents were jumping ship.
我四处奔走 把他们揽回来
I travelled around, signing them up.
几百号人呢
Hundreds of them.
其中有一个人管自己叫格茨曼
One of them was calling himself Gerstmann.
他在回俄罗斯的路上
He was on his way back to Russia
我们很确定他将会被处死
and we were pretty sure he was going to be executed.
飞机在德里停留了24小时 就在那段时间里
Plane had a 24-hour lay-over at Delhi and that's how long I had
我必需说服他投奔我们
to convince him to come over to us
别回去送死
instead of going home to die.
一个很小的房间里...
There's a little room.
我坐这儿 他坐那儿
I'm sitting here. He's sitting there.
美国人对他施了刑
The Americans had had him tortured.
他已经没有了指甲
He had no fingernails.
热得要命
It's incredibly hot.
我很累 只想把这事了结了然后回家
I'm very tired and all I want to do is get this over with and get back home.
当时正跟安恩闹矛盾
Things weren't going well with Ann.
我用老套路劝他..
I give him the usual pitch.
来西方吧 我们可以给你舒适的生活
"Come to the West and we can give you a comfortable life,
在审讯之后
"after questioning."
他怎么说?
What did he say?
想想你的妻子
"Think of your wife.
你有妻子吧?
"You have a wife, don't you?
还有 我给你带了点香烟
"Here. I brought you some cigarettes, by the way.
用我的打火机吧
"Use my lighter.
我们可以安排她与你团聚
"We could arrange for her to join you. We have a lot of stock to trade.
我们有一大批囤货可以交易
要是你回去 她会被流放 为她考虑考虑吧
"If you go back, she'll be ostracised. Think of her.
想想...
"Think about..."
我一直...
I kept on...
...说老婆的事儿
...harping on about the damn wife,
之后跟他说了很多我自己的事...
telling him more about me than...
其实我早该起身离去
I should have walk ed out, of course.
但是出于某种原因 我觉得救出这个人很重要
我跟你其实没有太多的不一样
"We're not so very different you and I.
你和我花了一辈子时间
"We've both spent our lives
来寻找对方制度上的弱点
"looking for the weaknesses in one another's systems.
难道你不觉得是时候承认
"Don't you think it's time to recognise
你的一方和我的一方都是没有东西值得我们卖命的吗?
"there is as little worth on your side as there is on mine?"
没说一句话
Never said a word.
一个字都没说
Not one word.
第二天早上他坐飞机回去了
And the next morning he got back on his plane.
把那包烟还给了我 没有碰过
He handed the pack of cigarettes back to me, untouched.
这个老烟枪
This was a chain-smok er, mind.
怀着必死的心飞走了
And he flew off to what he presumed would be his death.
他留着我的打火机
He k ept my lighter.
那是一份礼物
It was a gift.
“给乔治 安恩赠”
"To George from Ann.
“我的最爱”
"All my love."
他就是卡拉?
That was Karla.
他宁愿飞回去送死也不愿意投降?
He went back to die rather than giving in.
嗯 也就是这一次 我知道了他不是不可战胜的
Yes, and that's how I k now he can be beaten.
他是个狂热分子
Because he's a fanatic.
狂热分子总是隐藏着猜疑
And the fanatic is always concealing a secret doubt.
他长什么样?
What did he look lik e?
我记不起来了
I can't remember.
今天以后 彼得
After today, Peter,
你要小心他们在监视你
you have to assume they're watching you.
想想还有什么东西要收拾
If there's anything you need tidied up,
趁现在
now is the time.
快好了
Nearly done.
For God's sak e.
Sometimes I think they're all sharing the same moronic brain.
如果你有了别人 可以坦白告诉我
If there's someone else, you can tell me.
我是成年人了
I'm a grown-up.
我知道 这是一个快乐的圣诞节
I know. It's just going to be such a wonderful Christmas.
抱歉
Excuse me.
# And I was too proud to give in
# I had to learn the hard way
彼得 你准备好了
- # That pride... # - Peter, when you're ready
播出来
Put it on now.
大家注意!
Everybody!
-杰里 -乔治
- Jerry. - George.
-彼得 -杰里
- Peter. - Jerry.
我要跟你谈谈
I need to talk to you.
吉姆・普莱多被杀的那晚
About the night J im Prideaux was killed.
你是值勤员 没错吧?
You were duty officer, weren't you?
是的 那天晚上老总让我负责接电话
Yeah. Control ask ed me to man the phones that night.
他说有人为圆场在执行特殊行动
He said someone was doing a special job for the service.
他要找一个信得过的人
He wanted someone he could trust.
'Hurricane Henry set to be ridden by Ray Walsh at 7:2... '
长官 出了点事
There's been a bit of a panic, sir.
消息来自英国外交部常驻书记
This is from the FO resident clerk.
一条匈牙利新闻简报 长官
A Hungarian news bulletin.
一名化名为埃利斯的英国间谍
"British spy, work name Ellis,
使用伪造的匈牙利证件出行
"travelling with false Hungarian papers,
在布达佩斯试图绑架一名未提及姓名的匈牙利将军
"has attempted to kidnap an unnamed Hungarian General in Budapest.
他中枪了
"He's been shot.
其他逮捕行动也将展开
"Other arrests imminent."
长官 可以告诉我个大概吗?
Can I have a brief, please?
长官　你要我装聋扮哑吗?　长官?
Sir? Do you want me to deny it, sir?
给我说个大概啊 长官
老总一点也不松口
'I couldn't get a word out of Control.
我只好依照紧急情况处理指示来做
'So I followed protocol and went for the emergency list.'
你打电话去我家
You rang my house.
想碰碰运气看你从柏林回来了没有
J ust on the off-chance you were back from Berlin.
你说了什么?
What did you say?
-喂 你好 -你好 史迈利太太
- 'Hello? ' - Hello, Mrs Smiley.
我是杰里 局里的杰里・威斯特贝
It's Jerry. Jerry Westerby from the office.
刚才出了点事
Just that there'd been a bit of a crisis.
她说你还没回来 就这些了
Ann said you wasn't back yet and that was it.
接着说
Go on.
整个局面都失控了
All hell brok e loose.
军方为匈牙利坦克在边界的活动大为不满
Military yelling about Hungarian tank s on the border.
Lacon and the minister baying at the door.
拉康和大臣在门口吵得不可开交
谢天谢地比尔・海顿及时出现了
Thank Christ Bill Haydon turned up when he did.
-海顿先生 -别吵
- Mr Haydon. - Not now.
海顿先生!
Mr Haydon!
出去!
Out!
-告诉我 -我有试过联系你的
- Tell me. - I tried to get hold of you.
我在俱乐部的电报上只看到消息的一半 告诉我
I got half a story on the tick er tape at my club. Tell me.
吉姆・普莱多中枪了
Jim Prideaux's been shot.
打电话去匈牙利大使馆
Get me the H ungarian embassy.
告诉你们的主子
You tell your masters what will happen
要是普莱多少了根头发 后果很严重...
if one hair on J im Prideaux's head is damaged.
打电话给伊斯特哈斯 叫他召回咱们在匈牙利的特工
Get Esterhase on the phone. Tell him to call in the Hungarian agents.
是的 长官
Yes, sir.
有更多他的消息吗? 长官
Any more news on him? Sir?
天呐
Oh, God.
还要去他的公寓 把相关的东西销毁
We need to get down to his flat, clear out anything link ed.
海顿在他的俱乐部听到的消息?
Haydon heard the news at his club?
在萨维尔
凌晨一点半的时候 无线电已经不工作了
At 1: 30? The tick er-tape wouldn't have been running.
那他怎么知道的?
So how did he know?
-天呐 乔治... -彼得!
- Jesus, George. - Peter!
-他怎么知道的? -这事你别去想了
- How could he have known? - It's not what you think.
-那他究竟怎么知道的? -因为那天晚上他在我的家
- Then how did he know? - He was at my house that night.
旅途愉快?
Good flight?
嗯
Yes.
很不错
Pleasant enough.
我只是路过 想着应该拜访一下
I was just passing. I thought I'd call in.
安恩当时在床上 但是她坚持要起来
Ann was in bed. She insisted on getting up.
她说她马上下来
She said she'd be down in a minute.
我带了这个过来 画得实在够憋脚的
That's what I'm dropping off. It's an awful daub really.
不过安恩好像挺喜欢的
But Ann expressed a liking.
她怎么还不下来?
What's k eeping her?
加油
Keep going.
加油 孩子们 坚持住
Come on, lads. Keep up.
加油 比尔!
Come on, Bill!
-眼镜戴上了吗? 小胖 -是的 先生
- Got your specs on, J umbo? - Yes, sir.
过来
Come here.
在那边的人是谁?
Who's that fellow down there?
我不知道 先生
I don't know, sir.
他是谁?
Who is he?
乞丐?
Beggar man?
盗贼?
Thief?
为什么他不往这儿看?
Why doesn't he look this way, hm?
要是一群小子在空地里乱开着一辆车 你怎么会不看一眼?
Wouldn't you if you saw a bunch of boys flogging a car round a field?
他怎么了? 他不喜欢我们吗?
What's the matter with him? Doesn't he lik e us?
别让一些怪人晃来晃去
I don't hold with odd-bods hanging around.
他可能要把阿尔维斯偷走
He might steal the Alvis.
-那是什么啊? -英国最好的车! 先生
- Which is? - The best car in England, sir.
好孩子
Good lad.
你是怎样接到布达佩斯的任务的?
How were you briefed for the Budapest mission?
老总把我叫到肯辛顿的公寓
Control ask ed me to come to a flat in Kensington.
这个烂苹果 吉姆
There's a rotten apple, Jim.
我们要把它找出来
And we have to find it.
你是怎么理解的? 吉姆
What did you mak e of it, Jim?
老总的理论?
Control's theory?
我觉得老总疯了
I thought it was madness.
我知道是他们五个中的一个
I know that it is one of five men.
你只需要告诉我他们的代号
All I want from you is one code name.
阿勒莱恩
Alleline.
锅匠
Tink er.
海顿
Haydon.
裁缝
Tailor.
布兰德
Bland.
士兵
Soldier.
我们不用“水手” 因为与“裁缝”的发音太接近
We drop Sailor. It's too close to Tailor.
“富人”好像不太适合
And Rich Man doesn't seem to be applicable.
伊斯特哈斯
Esterhase.
穷人?
Poor Man.
还有第五个?
And the fifth?
史迈利
Smiley.
这想法太疯了
I thought it was madness.
竟然觉得你是他们其中的一个
To think that any one of you could have been a traitor.
彻底地疯了
Absolute madness.
但你还是去了
'But you still went.
为什么?
'Why? '
我去 是因为老总叫我去
'I went because Control ask ed me to go.
我是履行职责
'Lt's called doing one's duty.
我在车站与那个带我去见将军的跑腿碰面
'At the station I met the legman supposed to tak e me to the General.
侍应生被吓坏了
'The waiter must have panick ed.
本来是一个简单的小任务
'Lt was meant to be a simple snatch job.
他们把我送到了军方医院
'They drove me to some military hospital,
然后押上了运输机
'and then put me on a transport plane.
一开始的时候我还分得清我们向着东方走
'I could tell by the stars we were heading east.
我们一直审我...
'Then they work ed me for...
...不知道审多久了
'... I don't know how long.
几个星期 或许几个月
'Week s, maybe months.'
你跟他们说什么了?
What did you tell them?
所有的事
Everything.
我尽全力坚持着 为所有人争取时间逃出匈牙利
I held on for as long as I could to let everyone get the hell out of there.
他们有逃掉吗?
Did they?
我的人都在匈牙利 他们逃出去了吗?
My network s in H ungary, did they get out?
没有 他们被端了
No, they were blown.
传闻说你为了自保 把他们都供出来了
The story is you blew them to save your own skin.
他们审完了以后 有个小个子就出现了
'After the interrogators had cleared out, this little fellow turned up.
看上去像个神父
'Look ed lik e a priest.
那才是来真格的
'That's when they really started on me.'
你最后的防线是什么?
What was your last line of defence, hm?
地鼠
The mole.
老总的疯狂理论
Control's crazy theory.
我一直深埋着 他们决不会从我这儿套出来的
I was going to bury that so deep they'd never get it out of me.
-结果却成了笑话 -为什么?
- Which was a jok e. - Why?
因为他们早就知道
Because they already knew.
他们想知道的是老总调查到哪一步了
All they wanted to know was how far Control had got in his investigation.
不 我不认识她
No, I don't know her.
他们问了我什么事吗?
Did they ask about me at all?
有
Yes.
那个小个子问了
The little fellow did.
他说了我什么?
What did he say about me?
他拿着个香烟打火机
He had this cigarette lighter.
他拿着打火机我面前晃来晃去
He k ept flashing it about for me to see it.
把题词给我看
Showed me the inscription.
“给乔治 ...” “安恩赠”
- "To George..." - "...from Ann.
“我的最爱”
"All my love."
是卡拉
Karla.
很奇怪
'lt was odd.
他们把我送回了英格兰
'They sent me back to England.
直接到沙拉特汇报情况 （沙拉特：圆场培训新特务的机构，位于沙拉特）
'Straight to Sarratt for debriefing.'
他说他脱身后 在护理院受审的时候 有一个人找过他
He said when he was being debriefed at the N ursery, he had a visitor.
谁?
Who?
托比・伊斯特哈斯
'Toby Esterhase.
他给了吉姆一千镑 和一辆阿尔维斯
'He gave him ?1,000 and an Alvis.'
叫他就此人间蒸发别再回来
Told him he was dead now. Couldn't come back.
像喝了孟婆汤一样 忘掉所有发生过的事情
Had to become a lotus eater, forget everything that happened.
包括老总的那套说法
Control's theory.
锅匠 裁缝... 所有所有
Tink er, Tailor. All of it.
这正是我不解的地方
Yes, that's what I thought.
伊斯特哈斯究竟是如何得知“锅匠 裁缝”的呢?
How on earth did Esterhase hear about Tink er, Tailor?
伊琳娜老是跟我说起 在莫斯科中心里
'lrina k ept telling me in Moscow Centre
大人物们那些笑得止不住的笑声
'everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
她说卡拉非常为之骄傲
'She told me Karla was very proud of this.
圆场视为金矿的东西不过是垃圾 全是来自莫斯科
'She said everything the Circus think s is gold is shit, made in Moscow.
伊琳娜老是跟我说起 在莫斯科中心里
'Lrina k ept telling me in Moscow Centre
大人物们那些笑得止不住的笑声
'everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
不 我知道附近有家旅馆 他们有几个小房子
'No, I had a hotel nearby. They do have some seedy rooms.
伊琳娜老是跟我说起 在莫斯科中心里
'Lrina k ept telling me in Moscow Centre
大人物们那些笑得止不住的笑声
'everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
她说卡拉非常为之骄傲...
'She told me Karla was very proud of this... '
“圆场视为金矿的东西不过是垃圾”
'She said everything the Circus think s is gold is shit.'
不开会了 说的够清楚没?
This meeting is not taking place. Is that clear?
很清楚 大臣
Perfectly, Minister.
在城里的某座宅子
There is a house somewhere in this city
是阿勒莱恩和其他几个人 跟“巫术”的伦敦代表碰头的地方
where Alleline and the others meet Witchcraft's London representative.
我以为拉康跟你说得够明白了
I thought Lacon had made it clear to you.
“巫术”的事你别插手!
Keep your nose bloody well out of Witchcraft's business.
我就是遵照着拉康的意思办事
It's Lacon's advice I'm following.
是你让我跟老总的足迹调查下去
You told me to follow in Control's footsteps.
我不管是谁的意思 老总给我们丢下这么个该死的烂摊子
I wouldn't consider that sound advice, given the mess Control left us with.
害得阿勒莱恩 不妨直说 还害我
It has tak en Alleline and, if I may say so, myself
花了多少时间才让圆场重新走上正轨
this long to get us back in the game.
阿勒莱恩和其余几个人要见的人正是波里雅科夫
The man Alleline and the others meet is called Polyak ov.
你以为他负责把“巫术情报”送到你手上
'From Witchcraft to you.
而实际上他是负责把地鼠的情报
'His real role is to receive information from the mole
送回给卡拉
'to tak e back to Karla.'
这...这不可能
That, er... That's not possible.
有可能
Made possible.
有你帮忙说服财政部支付了宅子的费用
By you in the house you persuaded the Treasury to pay for.
“巫术情报”千真万确 是金矿啊!
Witchcraft's intelligence is genuine. It's been gold.
看似诱人 其实都是鸡毛蒜皮的东西
It's just enough glitter amongst the chick en feed.
老总不相信奇迹 也不相信“巫术”
Control didn't believe in miracles or in Witchcraft.
但因为你的怠慢失职和贪婪
But you were lazy and greedy
就想方设法赶他出局 从而让卡拉趁虚而入
and so you hounded him out of the Circus and you let Karla in.
你们已经跟美方展开谈判 磋商交换情报的事宜
You opened negotiations to exchange intelligence with the Americans.
他们给圆场的情报也会一字不落去到克里姆林宫
What they tell the C ircus, they'll be telling the Kremlin.
“巫术”提供的所谓“金矿”情报
Witchcraft's information, the "gold" Karla let you have,
他想引诱上钩的不是你
it wasn't to lure you.
而是美国佬
It was to lure the Americans.
现在
Now,
你还想邀功吗?
do you want to tak e credit for that?
我们能怎么办?
What can we do?
我们手里有一样地鼠想要的东西
We have one thing the mole wants.
-如果要我去巴黎... -你要去...
- If I go to Paris... - You'll go.
如果要我...去巴黎
If I go to Paris,
我要你们保证把伊琳娜带回来
I want your word that you will get Irina back.
我不管你们拿谁去换 反正我不玩了
I don't care who you have to trade. And I am out.
我想要一个家 我才不想落得你们这些人的下场...
I want a family, thank you. I do not want to end up lik e you lot.
你们把她带回来
You will get her back.
我会尽力的 里基
I'll do my utmost, Ricki.
噢 你好 乔治
Oh, hello, George.
你好
Hello.
我想跟你谈谈忠诚 托比
I want to talk about loyalty, Toby.
老总招你进来的 是不是?
Control recruited you, didn't he?
他看你在维也纳一个博物馆里挨饿
Found you starving in a museum in Vienna.
还是通缉犯
A wanted man.
听说他救了你一命
Saved your life, I heard.
然而 到了关键时刻
And yet when the time came,
让你在老总和阿勒莱恩之间作选择的时候
when it came to picking sides between him and Alleline,
你就没犹豫过?
you didn't hesitate.
或许这能归因于你经历过战争
That's understandable, perhaps, with your war experience.
这么多年来你能生存下来
You survived this long, I suppose, because of your ability to change sides.
我想这跟你慧眼识主的能力不无关系
还真倒戈自如啊
Serve any master.
这话... 这话从何说起呀 乔治?
What? What's... What's this about, George?
从你改投哪方阵营说起 托比
It's about which master you've been serving, Toby.
情报泄露了 托比
'I ntelligence has been leak ed, Toby.
有人一直从圆场盗取情报
'Someone's been taking files from the Circus.
不 不 不 不 不
'No, no, no, no. No.'
这是个误会 你误解了
This is a mistak e, a misunderstanding.
文件都交给了一个苏联外交参事 是不是?
Files were delivered to a Russian attach? weren't they?
是的
Yes.
我也承认是我送出去的
'And, yes, I delivered them.'
但潘西也有份
'But so did Percy Alleline.'
好孩子
Good boy.
比尔
'Bill Haydon.
还有罗埃・布兰德
'And so did Roy Bland.'
有些事并非如我们想象中那样 乔治
Things aren't always what they seem, George.
你是知道的
You should know that.
苏联当局以为波里雅科夫...
Look, Moscow think s Polyak ov's...
...是在为他们效力
...working for them.
所以我们时不时给他点无关重要的情报带回去充数
Every now and then we give him the odd file to tak e back to them.
都是些鸡毛蒜皮的情报 算是给他上司的交代
Chick en feed, just to k eep his bosses happy.
但其实波里雅科夫是我们的人
But Polyak ov's our Joe.
-是一项大行动的关键人物 -你指“巫术行动”吗?
- He's a part of a big operation. - Operation Witchcraft.
这个我知道
Yes, I know.
乔治
George.
-拜托 我不该受到这样的待遇 -是谁派你去见吉姆
- Please, I don't deserve this. - Who gave you the message
叫他忘掉“锅匠裁缝”的事?
for Jim Prideaux to forget about Tink er, Tailor?
-布兰德 -那么铲除康妮・沙赫斯的事呢?
- Bland. - To get rid of Connie Sachs?
-威斯特贝呢? -布兰德
- Westerby? - Bland.
也许是海顿
Or Haydon.
我不记得了 反正他们其中一个
I don't know. One of them.
也可能是潘西 不
Or maybe Percy. No.
我不知道是谁
Well, I don't know who.
你只是个信差
You're just the messenger.
在他们之间跑来跑去
Running between them all.
你有为“巫师”效力吗?
Anything to serve Witchcraft.
我非常清楚你们的终极秘密
I know all about your secret source.
我也知道你所不知道的
And I know something you don't.
我知道他是谁
I know who he is.
他就是卡拉
He's Karla.
你们中有人给了波里雅科夫货真价实的机密情报
'One of you has been giving Polyak ov the crown jewels. '
-我不知情 -你还在通缉名单上吗? 托比
- I did not know. - Are you still a wanted man, Toby?
-看 乔治 我真不知情 我... -你站错队了
- Look, George, I didn't know. I... - You pick ed the wrong side.
你得相信我 我绝不会...
No, you've got to believe me.
乔治 别
George, please.
我是忠诚的!
I am loyal.
我... 我是忠诚的!
I... I am loyal.
不要... 不要... 不要送我回去
Don't... Don't... Don't send me back.
不要 乔治
Please, George.
不要送我回去
Don't send me back.
把地址给我
Give me the address.
你们与波里雅科夫见面的地点
Where do you meet Polyak ov?
嘿 嘿! 乖狗狗 别吵!
Hey, hey! Dog, dog, be quiet!
怎么回事? 你是谁?
What is this? Who are you?
-麦克雷格太太? -是的
-安全信号是什么? -通风管道
- What are the safety signals? - The air vent.
打开的话表示一切正常 关闭则表示不能内进
Open and all's well, closed and you're not to enter.
窃听器在哪儿?
And the microphone?
彼得?
Peter?
“男孩站在燃烧的甲板上 除他外无人生还”
The boy stood on the burning deck whence all but he had fled
“火焰照亮了战争的残骸 火光中他孤零零地站在尸体堆中”
The flame that lit the battle's wreck shone brightly o'er the dead
“他的身影却是那样绝美而明亮 命中注定驾驭暴风之上”
'Beautiful and proud he stood as born to rule the storm
“血肉之躯 虽然渺小 却为之骄傲”
'A creature of blood, a proud though child-lik e form'
“火焰在翻腾...”
- The flames rolled on...
谢谢 再见
Merci. Au revoir.
继续
Go on.
局里出动了全部人马在找你
The whole service is looking for you.
他们找到你非活剥了你的皮不可
- They'll skin you alive if they find you. - Maybe I want them to find me.
或许我希望他们找到我
你可以回家了 把书放回原处 钥匙插到机子里
You can go now. Leave the book s and put the k eys in the machines.
不 本 你留下
No, Ben stays here.
里基・塔尔声称手中有更多关系圆场安危的情报
Ricki Tarr claims to have information vital to the safeguarding of the Circus.
史迈利先生?
'Mr Smiley? '
有计程车驶进圆场
Taxi approaching Circus.
锅匠
Tink er.
裁缝
Tailor.
这个是士兵
Here comes Soldier.
人齐了
'Full house.'
好 继续 大声念出来
- Well, go on then. Read it out loud. - "Personal for Tarr from Alleline.
“阿勒莱恩致塔尔的私人信息”
“在满足你的请求前我们需要澄清”
"Require clarification before meeting your request.
“前引号 更多关系圆场安危的情报 后引号”
"Quote, information vital to safeguarding of the Circus, unquote
“不足以说明情况 需提供更多的情报”
"does not qualify, send further information."
这就对了嘛 姓潘西的 你就拖延时间吧
Ah! That's it, Percy, you k eep stalling.
我得警告你 本 园场里有奸细
I warn you, Ben. We've got some really lousy people in this outfit.
你谁都不能轻信
I wouldn't trust a fucking one of them.
“会议结束”
'The meeting's over.
“他们要走了”
'They're leaving.'
克拉道克斯说我不用几天就可以离开了
Craddox says I'll be off in a few days.
我一直在想 在莫斯科我会有多惦念板球这游戏啊
I k eep thinking how much I'm going to miss the crick et in Moscow.
我很希望你能帮我跑跑腿
I was rather hoping you might do a little light housek eeping for me.
我会尽力的
If I can.
有个女孩 你能替我给她点钱么?
There's a girl. Give her some money, would you?
帮我编个故事
And give her a good cover story.
如果能让她好过点 就跟她说我爱她
If it helps, tell her I love her.
全在那儿了
It's all there.
还有个男孩 给他塞点堵口费
And there's a boy, too. Slip him a few quid to shut him up.
我太清楚审讯人惯用的伎俩了
I know the inquisitors' bag of trick s. I taught most of them.
他们几乎都是我教出来的
我有点激动
It's just a reaction.
也许是太激动了 随便你怎么想
An over-reaction, if you lik e.
我有一两个问题
I did have one or two questions.
-关于普莱多的 -该死!
- About Prideaux. - Goddamn it!
-是我把他救回来的 不是吗? -没错 是你
- I got him back, didn't I? - Yes, yes, you did.
那是你的功劳
我很意外卡拉居然没有毙了他
I am surprised Karla didn't have him shot.
还是你觉得
Or do you think he held back,
他之所以退缩是出于对你的微妙情感?
out of delicacy towards you?
普莱多赴匈牙利执行任务前是不是去找过你?
Did Prideaux come and see you before he left on the Hungarian mission?
没错 事实就是这样
Yes, as a matter of fact he did.
为了说什么吗?
To say what?
为了警告你
To warn you.
因为他心知肚明
Because he knew deep down
那个人从始至终就是你
it was you all along.
你也一样
So did you.
我不得不选择立场 乔治
I had to pick a side, George.
这是个两难的抉择 差不多就是个道德难题
It was an aesthetic choice as much as a moral one.
西方国家越来越丑恶
And the West has become so very ugly.
你不觉得吗?
Don't you think?
卡拉有没有想过让你接管圆场?
Did Karla ever consider having you tak e over the Circus?
我才不是他的走卒!
I'm not his bloody office boy!
那你是什么呢? 比尔
What are you, then, Bill?
我就是一个功成名就的人
I'm someone who's made his mark.
有什么需要我帮你带给安恩的吗?
Is there anything particular you want me to pass on to Ann?
喔 那只是工作需要 乔治 我想你应该能明白的
Oh, that was nothing personal, George. I hope you understand that.
卡拉说你是个厉害角色
Karla said you were good,
不容小觑
the one we had to worry about.
不过你确实也有死穴
But you do have a blind spot.
他料想如果我当了安恩的公开情人
He reck oned if I was known to be Ann's lover,
你便不那么容易能揭穿我了
you wouldn't be able to see me straight.
他是对的
And he was right.
一定程度上
Up to a point.
我给您做了样东西 先生
I made this for you, sir.
我不想再看到你到处闲逛
I don't want you hanging around here any more.
从现在开始离我远点
Keep away from me from now on.
-去找大伙玩吧 -但是...
- Go and join the others. - But...
叫你去... 你就去吧
Just... Just bloody join in, will you?
他妈的找他们玩去!
Go and play, damn you!
你可以查一下吗? 杰里
Could you check, Jerry?